<idea-plugin>
    <id>com.protonail.bbolt</id>
    <name>bbolt Database</name>
    <vendor email="vistone@users.noreply.github.com" url="https://github.com/vistone/bbolt">vistone</vendor>

    <description><![CDATA[
        <p>A visual browser and JDBC driver integration for BoltDB-compatible embedded key-value databases inside JetBrains IDEs.</p>

        <h3>Supported database formats</h3>
        <ul>
            <li><b>bbolt (BoltDB)</b> — the Go ecosystem's embedded key-value store (github.com/etcd-io/bbolt). Files are opened through a native library (bolt-jna) for full read/write access.</li>
            <li><b>jammdb</b> — a Java/JVM-friendly BoltDB-compatible store (github.com/pjtatlow/jammdb). Files are parsed directly in Java, including support for overflow pages that store values larger than a single page.</li>
        </ul>
        <p>The plugin auto-detects the underlying format by the file's magic number, so the same UI works for both.</p>

        <h3>Features</h3>
        <ul>
            <li>Open and browse <code>.db</code> files in a dedicated tool window</li>
            <li>Navigate bucket hierarchies in a tree view (nested buckets supported)</li>
            <li>View key-value pairs of any bucket, including large values that span multiple pages</li>
            <li>Execute SQL-like queries on buckets (bbolt, via JDBC)</li>
            <li>Format auto-detection — no manual configuration required</li>
        </ul>
    ]]></description>

    <change-notes><![CDATA[
        <b>1.0.16</b><br>
        Added release-grade cross-platform native packaging. GitHub Actions now builds the bbolt native library on Windows x86-64, Linux x86-64, macOS Intel, and macOS Apple Silicon runners, then packages all four native resources into one verified plugin zip.

        <br><br><b>1.0.15</b><br>
        Added Windows x86-64 platform support! The plugin now includes a precompiled `bolt.dll` native library for Windows, enabling bbolt database browsing on Windows systems. Added a cross-platform build script `build-native.sh` that automatically compiles native libraries for Linux, Windows, and macOS (on respective platforms). Updated README with compatibility documentation for all supported operating systems.

        <br><br><b>1.0.14</b><br>
        Fixed &quot;Failed to open database: timeout&quot; error when opening a bbolt database that is already locked by another process (e.g. etcd). The plugin now opens bbolt databases in <b>read-only mode</b> with a shared file lock (<code>LOCK_SH</code>) instead of an exclusive lock (<code>LOCK_EX</code>), and increased the lock-acquisition timeout from 5s to 60s. Read-only mode is the correct choice for a browser plugin — it never conflicts with the process that owns the database.

        <br><br><b>1.0.13</b><br>
        Fixed &quot;Open in bbolt Browser&quot; context menu not appearing for some database files. The bbolt detection was using <code>contentsToByteArray()</code> which loads the entire file into memory — for large database files this was slow enough that the action update timed out and the menu item never showed. Switched to streaming only the first 32 bytes via <code>getInputStream()</code> and added diagnostic logging for detection failures.

        <br><br><b>1.0.12</b><br>
        Fixed the bbolt magic-number detection in the &quot;Open in bbolt Browser&quot; context-menu action. The magic 0xED0CDAED lives in the meta struct, which starts after the 16-byte page header — the previous code checked offset 8 (inside the page header) so bbolt files were never recognized and the action never appeared for them. Now reads offset 16-19 (little-endian ED DA 0C ED). jammdb detection was already correct.

        <br><br><b>1.0.11</b><br>
        Replaced the double-click interception (which could leave binary garbage in the editor) with an explicit <b>"Open in bbolt Browser"</b> action in the project-view context menu. Right-click any database file (bbolt or jammdb, detected by magic number — any extension works) and choose <i>Open in bbolt Browser</i> to open it in the tool window. The action is only visible/enabled for files that are actually databases. The default double-click behavior is no longer intercepted, so binary files are not opened in the text editor by accident.

        <br><br><b>1.0.10</b><br>
        Fixed binary garbage showing in the editor area when double-clicking a database file. Replaced the <code>FileEditorProvider</code> approach (which still left a placeholder editor tab) with a <code>FileEditorManagerListener</code> subscribed via a <code>postStartupActivity</code>. Now when a database file is opened, it is redirected to the bbolt Browser tool window and the editor tab is closed immediately, so no binary content is ever shown in the editor.

        <br><br><b>1.0.9</b><br>
        Double-clicking a database file in the project view now opens it directly in the bbolt Browser tool window without leaving an editor tab open. The tool window is force-initialized if it has never been shown, and the editor tab is closed immediately so the database only appears in the tool window. Also raised the compatibility upper bound to build 261.* to support RustRover 2026.1.

        <br><br><b>1.0.8</b><br>
        Double-click a database file in the IDE project view to open it directly in the bbolt Browser tool window. Format is auto-detected by magic number, so any file extension works. A lightweight placeholder editor replaces the default text editor for binary database files, showing a hint that points to the tool window.

        <br><br><b>1.0.7</b><br>
        Tree view refinements: nodes now use distinct colors to differentiate database files (deep blue), buckets (dark teal), and keys (default foreground) instead of all-gray. Enabled classic angled tree connection lines (<code>JTree.lineStyle=Angled</code>) so parent-child relationships are visually clear.

        <br><br><b>1.0.6</b><br>
        Replaced the project icon with a vector SVG derived from the etcd logo (with the "etcd" wordmark removed). The SVG traces the hexagonal gear outline, the center hexagonal hole, and the two "eyes", using <code>fill-rule="evenodd"</code> for correct nesting. As a true vector icon, it scales cleanly to any size (13x13, 16x16, 32x32) without blurring or distortion. All primary icon locations (tool window, database nodes, bucket nodes, key nodes, file type) now use this icon.

        <br><br><b>1.0.5</b><br>
        Refined UI to match native JetBrains IDE look-and-feel: replaced raw <code>JToolBar</code>/<code>JButton</code> with <code>ActionToolbar</code> and <code>AnAction</code> (Open/Close/Refresh); switched from <code>JPanel</code> to <code>SimpleToolWindowPanel</code>; replaced <code>JTable</code> with <code>JBTable</code> (proper row height, empty-state text, header styling); replaced <code>JLabel</code> with <code>JBLabel</code> using context-help foreground color and small font for status/pagination; pagination buttons now use platform icons (<code>AllIcons.Actions.Back/Forward</code>); tree renderer distinguishes database/bucket nodes with proper icons and borders; bottom bar has a top border separator. Removed the <code>.db</code> extension filter from the file chooser — any file can be opened regardless of extension, with format auto-detected by magic number.

        <br><br><b>1.0.4</b><br>
        Support opening multiple database files simultaneously. Each open database appears as a separate top-level node in the bucket tree, with its own buckets and pagination state. Added a "Close" toolbar button to close the selected database. Fixed pagination button state updates: buttons are now reliably enabled/disabled after each page load, with stale-result guards to handle rapid bucket switching.

        <br><br><b>1.0.3</b><br>
        Pagination support for large buckets. Bucket contents are now loaded page by page (500 entries per page) instead of loading the entire bucket into memory, preventing OutOfMemoryError on databases with millions of entries. Added prev/next page navigation controls. Values larger than 64 KB are truncated in preview mode and can be fetched in full on demand via <code>getValue()</code>.

        <br><br><b>1.0.2</b><br>
        Fix <code>BufferUnderflowException</code> when reading jammdb buckets that contain large values spanning multiple pages (overflow pages). The reader now allocates a buffer covering all overflow pages before parsing leaf elements. Added unit tests covering the large-value scenario.

        <br><br><b>1.0.1</b><br>
        Added jammdb database format support alongside the existing bbolt support, with automatic format detection by magic number.

        <br><br><b>1.0.0</b><br>
        Initial release: JDBC driver integration and visual browser for bbolt databases.
    ]]></change-notes>

    <!-- Database plugin is optional (only available in Ultimate) -->
    <depends optional="true" config-file="com.protonail.bbolt.database.xml">com.intellij.database</depends>
    <depends>com.intellij.modules.platform</depends>

    <extensions defaultExtensionNs="com.intellij">
        <!-- Application service for native library loading -->
        <applicationService serviceImplementation="com.protonail.bolt.intellij.BoltNativeLoader"/>

        <!-- Startup activity to initialize native library on IDE start -->
        <postStartupActivity implementation="com.protonail.bolt.intellij.BoltStartupActivity"/>

        <!-- Tool window for bbolt browser -->
        <toolWindow
            id="bbolt Browser"
            anchor="right"
            icon="com.protonail.bolt.intellij.icons.BoltIcons.ToolWindow"
            factoryClass="com.protonail.bolt.intellij.ui.BoltToolWindowFactory"/>

        <!-- File type association for .db bolt files -->
        <fileType
            name="Bolt Database"
            implementationClass="com.protonail.bolt.intellij.file.BoltFileType"
            fieldName="INSTANCE"
            language="BBOLT"
            extensions="db"/>

        <!-- "Open in bbolt Browser" context-menu action for database files in the project view -->
        <!-- (registered below in <actions> section) -->

        <!-- Notification group -->
        <notificationGroup id="bbolt" displayType="BALLOON"/>
    </extensions>

    <actions>
        <!-- Action: Open bbolt database file -->
        <action
            id="com.protonail.bolt.intellij.actions.OpenBoltDatabaseAction"
            class="com.protonail.bolt.intellij.actions.OpenBoltDatabaseAction"
            text="Open bbolt Database"
            description="Open a bbolt database file for browsing"
            icon="com.protonail.bolt.intellij.icons.BoltIcons.Open">
            <add-to-group group-id="FileOpenGroup" anchor="last"/>
        </action>

        <!-- Action: Open in bbolt Browser (context menu in project view) -->
        <action
            id="com.protonail.bolt.intellij.actions.OpenInBoltBrowserAction"
            class="com.protonail.bolt.intellij.actions.OpenInBoltBrowserAction"
            text="Open in bbolt Browser"
            description="Open this database file in the bbolt Browser tool window"
            icon="com.protonail.bolt.intellij.icons.BoltIcons.Database">
            <add-to-group group-id="ProjectViewPopupMenu" anchor="first"/>
        </action>

        <!-- Action: Refresh current view (added to tool window toolbar via code) -->
        <action
            id="com.protonail.bolt.intellij.actions.RefreshAction"
            class="com.protonail.bolt.intellij.actions.RefreshAction"
            text="Refresh"
            description="Refresh the bbolt browser view"
            icon="com.protonail.bolt.intellij.icons.BoltIcons.Refresh"/>
    </actions>
</idea-plugin>
